<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A chrystian exhortation verye profitable gathered out of the holye scriptures, vnto the great comfort, and vtilitye, of euery faythfull soule, being in agony of death, vnto whom, it oughte to be rehersed, with lowd voyce, diuers and sundry times, if nede so require vnto the which is added, towarde the latter end a godly praier for the sick drawing to an ende of this life, with a catechisme, not onely to instruct the sicke, but also to refreshe his memorye, wyth the great mistery of our redemption. Translated out of Frenthe [sic] into Englyshe by Robart Heasse minister at Algate.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847824</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 465:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A chrystian exhortation verye profitable gathered out of the holye scriptures, vnto the great comfort, and vtilitye, of euery faythfull soule, being in agony of death, vnto whom, it oughte to be rehersed, with lowd voyce, diuers and sundry times, if nede so require vnto the which is added, towarde the latter end a godly praier for the sick drawing to an ende of this life, with a catechisme, not onely to instruct the sicke, but also to refreshe his memorye, wyth the great mistery of our redemption. Translated out of Frenthe [sic] into Englyshe by Robart Heasse minister at Algate.</title>
                  <author>Heasse, Robert, d. 1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote, dwellinge in Pawles Church-yarde at the signe of the Lucrece,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1566.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C¹⁵.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; considerable print show-through; all after C5 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:2"/>
            <p n="1">1 MVltitude of prebendes.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Multitude of prieſtes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Multitude of temples &amp; chapels</p>
            <p n="4">4 Multitude of aultars.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Diuers oblations and offringes</p>
            <p n="6">6 Worldly riches and pryde.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Idleneſſe and trwandiſſe of the ſhauen.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Multitude of harlotes.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Fained houres and prayers.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Deteſtable hypocriſy.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Deuourynge of widowes, orphans, &amp; the poore.</p>
            <p n="12">12 Renounſyng and deſtructyng of the death and paſſion of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>¶And ſo conſequently of the other, whyche are infinite.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>TO make ſhort y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> errour of the maſſe is moſte deadly &amp; hurtfull, aſwell to the goodes as to the perſones, in as much as it ſemeth to haue moſt ſigne of holynes and goodnes ſeinge that it is all execrable or curſed. Truely the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim wherewith the peſtilence is couered anoteth and greueth more greater tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, that is ſeene open.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraphs">
            <q>
               <p>Ite miſſa eſt. Amen</p>
               <bibl>3. Eſdras. 4. chap.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>¶Super omnia vincit veritas. Aboue all thyng the truthe ouercometh.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>MDXLVII.</p>
            <p>¶Printed at Wittenberge by Hans Lufte.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Chryſtian, exhortation verye profitable gathered out of the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, vnto the great comfort, and vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litye, of euery faythfull ſoule, being in agony of death, vnto whom, it oughte to be reherſed, with lowd voyce, diuers and ſundry times, if nede ſo require vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the which is added, towarde the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end a godly praier for the ſick draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing to an ende of this life, with a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, not onely to inſtruct the ſicke, but alſo to refreſhe his memorye, wyth the great miſtery of our redemption. Tranſlated out of Frenche into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe by Robart Heaſſe Miniſter at Algate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, by Thomas Purfoote,</hi> dwelling in Pawles Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde at the ſigne of the Lucrece.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1566.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraphs">
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:3"/>
            <q>
               <p>Death is ende, and the beginning of lyfe.</p>
               <bibl>Eccleſiaſtes .xvii.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ante lauguorem adhibe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinam et ante iudicium in, terroga teipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et in conſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu dei inuenies propitiatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <bibl>Apocalip. iii.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Si non vigilaueris veniam ad te tanquam fur et neſcis qua hora veniam ad te.</p>
               <bibl>Apocalip. xvi.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Beatus qui vigilat et cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit veſtimenta ſua nenudus ambulet et videant turpitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem eius.</p>
               <bibl>Math. 24.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke. 12.</bibl>
               <p>Eſtote parati quia neſcitis qua hora filius hominis ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus eſt.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:3"/>
            <head>Vnto the faithefull Reader, greting, in our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Earelye beloued Reader, I pray the take in good parte this preſent exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I haue here tranſlated out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French tounge, into thy vulgar tounge with greate thoughte and care vntill I of my part had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, I truſt to the gret com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of euerye faithfull perſon, that feareth God, to vſe &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, at the time of nede, when as it ſhall pleaſe god to call him out of this mortal and wretched worlde. But be aduertiſed that thou maiſte vſe it righte, that theſe thre letters. B.S.N. The firſt ſignifyeth brother, that is when thou ſpeakeſt vnto a man The ſeconde ſignifyeth ſuſter, a woman, and the thirde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth,
<pb facs="tcp:12885:4"/> that thou muſte name the partye ſicke, by his proper name, for he oughte not to be honoured, by names, either, of worldly, honours or worſhipes, But rather to reſiſt Satan the enemy of mannes ſoule, in and throughe the power of our lord and god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicke muſt be named, by his owne name, that he hath receiued, in the holy ſacrament of Baptiſme, and in ſo doinge thou ſhalt obey the Lord God, whom I beſeche of his infinite goodnes and mercye, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to be Good and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, both vnto thee and me in the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:12885:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Chriſten exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation whiche oughte to be</hi> recited wyth lowde voyce, before all faithfull people, beinge in agonye of deathe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL that is of God,<note place="margin">Ihon, vii.</note> heare the worde of God,<note place="margin">Math, vii.</note> and not onelye to heare it, but kepe it,<note place="margin">Hebre. i,</note> and put it in execution for all things ſhall haue an end and waxe olde as dothe a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.</note> but the worde of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth for euermore,<note place="margin">Rom, v,</note> and ſeing that it is ſo, that by one man ſinne is entered into the world and by ſinne, deathe and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all troubles and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities folowing, it is by iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation that the lyfe of man,<note place="margin">Rom, vii.</note> is but a continuall battaile vppon earthe, in ſuche ſorte, that the
<pb facs="tcp:12885:5"/> fleſhe fyghteth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit and the ſpirit againſt the deuill the world, and the fleſhe, which are enemies vnto oure ſoules, but folowing thapoſtles coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,<note place="margin">i, Peter, v.</note> to obtaine victorye in this ſpirituall battaile, you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſte conſtantly through fayth.<note place="margin">i, Ihon. v.</note> For the victorye whiche ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the worlde,<note place="margin">Hebre. xi,</note> is our faith whyche is a ſure and certayne knowledge of the loue of God towarde vs as by his ghoſpell he declareth him ſelfe to be our father and ſauiour, by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Ieſus Chryſt. Hauynge then ſuche a ſteadfaſt faithe for your principal foundation. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlye before the maieſtye of God that you are a poore and miſerable ſynner,<note place="margin">Pſal, li, Luke, xvii,</note> conceyued &amp; borne in iniquitye and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, enclined to doe euyll and that of your ſelfe ſo vnhable to
<pb facs="tcp:12885:5"/> doe anye Good by youre often tranſgreſing the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, in which ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, you haue deſerued by hys iuſte Iudgement, deathe and dampnacion vpon you, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge you are diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your ſelf to haue ſo often and many times offended hym and therefore you condempne your ſelfe and your vices wyth perfecte repentance, deſiringe that the grace of GOD redres your calamity. Pray then with ſuche a ſteadfaſt faithe.<note place="margin">Pſal, li,</note> If you cannot with the mouth, ſaye it with the hart, that God our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſte beninge, and full of mercye, doe not enter in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nor to rekening with vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 142,</note> but rather vouchſafe to haue pitie vpon you in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our lord and to wype awaye your offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſinnes by the merite of
<pb facs="tcp:12885:6"/> the deathe and paſſyon of the ſame Ieſus Chriſte, in whoſe name preſent vnto hym, hys holye Prayer that hee hathe taught vs, ſaying wyth a good harte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Math. vi,</note>Our father which art in. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.S.N</hi> Aknoweledge from the botome of your hearte your vnrighteouſneſſe, be ſorye for your ſynnes, repent you vnceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantlye,<note place="margin">Math, iii</note> and the kyngedome of God ſhall drawe nere, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that their is nether, righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Titus, iii,</note> innocencye nor anye good workes in you, nor from you,<note place="margin">Ephe, ii,</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal, li,</note> but contrarye wyſe, the ſonne of wrathe and Childe of perdicion, conceyued and borne in the ſynne of the olde Adam, you deſerue eternall death and dampnation,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> yet not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, let not thys, nor all the ſinnes of the world, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:12885:6"/> them, once fryghte you. For Ieſus Chriſte the eternall and true Sonne of God,<note place="margin">Rom, i,</note> hathe made him ſelfe perfect man con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Luke, i,</note> borne of the virgin Mary for to ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifye and clenſe you,<note place="margin">Math, i,</note> he hathe ſuffred vnder Ponce Pilate,<note place="margin">Phllip, 2</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers afflictions, iniuryes, and wronges, yeldinge him ſelfe as a ſlaue and Captiue,<note place="margin">Actes, 3,</note> for to ſet you at libertye,<note place="margin">Math, 27,</note> Ieſus Chriſte hath bene crucifyed and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the tre of the croſſe, to deliuer you from the maledicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perpetuall. Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eſay, 53,</note> is deade in ſheading, his precious bloude, for to waſhe you.<note place="margin">Apo, i,</note>
            </p>
            <p>For to redeeme you,<note place="margin">i, Peter, 1.</note> for to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you wholy from death and hell fyre, and from the myghte and power of Sathan,<note place="margin">Rom. vi,</note> Ieſus Chriſt hath bene buryed in the Sepulchre, for to bury all your ſynnes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he hath borne
<pb facs="tcp:12885:7"/> on his ſhoulders and hath wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them out,<note place="margin">Actes, i,</note> Ieſus Chriſte is deſcended into hell ſuffring an extreame agonye, for to deliuer you, from al paines and griefes of death. Ieſus Chriſt is ryſen from death,<note place="margin">i, Cori, rv, Actes, i. Colio. iii.</note> for to make you riſe in your proper bodye to a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous immortality. Ieſus Chriſt is aſcended into the Heauens, for to make you aſcende after him.<note place="margin">i. Ihon, ii,</note> Ieſus Chriſt is ſet on the right hande of God his father almighty,<note place="margin">Hebre, vii,</note> being your aduocate and interceſſor towardes hym and the atonement for all your ſynnes.<note place="margin">Math. xv, Pa, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</note> We looke that he ſhall come to Iudge the quicke and the dead,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> for to render to euery one according to his deds. But to his electe whiche beleue in him, their Synnes ſhal not be imputed, for he wil iuſtify them throughe his grace,<note place="margin">Math, xxv,</note> and make them to raigne with him in the
<pb facs="tcp:12885:7"/> heauenly throne, worlde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ende.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Suche is the great meſtery of our redemption, the whiche throughe the power of the holye Ghoſte, you oughte fermelye to beleue, it to be done for your ſaluacion. And doubt not,<note place="margin">Ephe, i,</note> but that by the merite of Ieſus chriſt chiefe of his church you be a member incorporated vnto the ſame, thankinge hym with gret humilite, that he hath vouchſafed to geeue you grace to haue beene aſſociated in the felowſhip and company of hys faithfull,<note place="margin">Math, iiii,</note> feeding you with hys holye worde, of his bodye,<note place="margin">i, Cor, xi,</note> and of his precious bloude, acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledginge as fully perſwaded, of the great mercye and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God by the remiſſion of all your ſynnes,<note place="margin">Rom, v,</note> the which is done vnto you,<note place="margin">i, Cor, xv,</note> by Ieſus Chriſt who will make you riſe again in the
<pb facs="tcp:12885:8"/> laſte daye, and their to raigne with hym in the life eternall,<note place="margin">Marke, 16,</note> which he hath promyſed to all thoſe that beleue in him beyng baptiſed in his name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Nowe ſeynge you haue ſuch a faith doubte not to receiue the promeſſe of faythe. For God is true,<note place="margin">Rom, iii,</note> he is not a lier as man is, Heauen and Earthe ſhall paſſe,<note place="margin">Math, 24,</note> but the worde of god ſhall laſt euermore, God is your father and maker,<note place="margin">Eſay, 40,</note> you are hys creature &amp; worke of his hands he made you not to leeſe you.<note place="margin">Gene, i,</note> For he is the ſauiour of all men and willeth not the deathe of a ſinner,<note place="margin">1, Timo, 2,</note> but rather that he ſhould tourne from his ſinne, by faith full repentance and ſo be ſaued. Wherefore I heare pronounce vnto you,<note place="margin">Ieremy,</note> in the name of God, that by and throughe his great goodnes and mercye:<note place="margin">Titus, iii.</note> you haue full forgeeuenes and remiſſion
<pb facs="tcp:12885:8"/> of all your ſinnes,<note place="margin">1, Timo, 1,</note> by the onely merite of his dere ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord in the ſheding of his precious bloud.<note place="margin">Actes, 4.</note> For he is the propiciation,<note place="margin">Apoca, 1, 1, Ihon. 2.</note> not onelye of all youre ſynnes but of all the ſinnes of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt ſaithe that all thinges are poſſible to thoſe that beleue.<note place="margin">Math, 17,</note> Beleue then withoute doubtinge that Ieſus Chriſt puttinge on our fleeſhe, hathe made him ſelfe perfecte man, dying for you, bearing all your ſinnes on his bodie, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhe and wype them oute.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Offer to god the precious death of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt and by the merite of the ſame death and paſſion, demannde of him mercye and forgeuenes, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge from the botome of youre harte in and with greate humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and repentaunce.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:9"/>
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie God and hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly father, ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto mee, poore and miſerable Synner,<note place="margin">Rom, iii,</note> for the loue of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſte my Lorde and ſauiour.<note place="margin">Ihon, xiiii,</note> And by the mirite of his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vouchſafe to receiue my ſoule whom I commend in to thy handes.<note place="margin">Math, 26,</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal, 30,</note>Haue your full confidence in God,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> for ſeing that God is with you, nothinge ſhall be againſt you. For Ieſus Chriſt which is the inmaculate lambe hath van<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quiſhed all thinges for you,<note place="margin">Eſay. 6.</note> he hath offered him ſelfe once for you, and by the ſame onelye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, hathe wholye ouercome all your ſynnes he hathe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d all your infirmities:<note place="margin">Heb. 7, &amp;, 9</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes, abhomynation and obligacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. With this good
<pb facs="tcp:12885:9"/> Lord Ieſus Chriſt God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath geuen you all thyngs ſtrengthen you in Ieſus Chriſt who hathe called you,<note place="margin">Rom, viii.</note> by his Prophetes, Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Eſay, 55,</note> and Euangeliſts to come frely vnto him ſaying. All y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are thurſty come vnto the great fountaine.<note place="margin">Math, xi,</note> Come vnto mee all ye that tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uayle and are laden, and I will eaſe you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Beleue ſteadfaſtlye that Ieſus Chriſt hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you of all your ſinnes,<note place="margin">i, Ihon, v,</note> and hathe reconciled you vnto God his Father, vnto whome with great reuerence and harty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce ſay from the botome of your heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty and eternall Lorde God,<note place="margin">Rom. iii, Ihon, xiiii,</note> be mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me, pore and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner for thy
<pb facs="tcp:12885:10"/> ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, my Lorde and ſauiour. And by the merite and worthynes of his death and paſſion,<note place="margin">Mathe, 26,</note> vouchſafe to receiue my ſoule into thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.<note place="margin">Pſal, 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>,</note> Amen,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Haue hope: for truth it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will receiue your ſoule as his owne, for the loue of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt which is the ſauiour and redemer of all thoſe that beleue in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marke, 16, Deute, 18, Pſal, 11, Eſay. 53, Ge, 3, &amp;, 22,</note>Moyſes and all the prophetes haue witneſſed that al nations ſhall receiue ſaluation and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely by and through Ieſus Chriſt the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts doe teſtifye that Ieſus Chriſte came not to call the righteous,<note place="margin">Mathe, 9,</note> but ſinners to repentaunce.<note place="margin">Ihon, x,</note> And to geeue his ſoule for the redemption of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye.<note place="margin">Luke, 21,</note> For he hath ſhed his precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloude, for the remiſſion of ſinnes. Beleue then, and doute
<pb facs="tcp:12885:10"/> not at all,<note place="margin">Hebre. i,</note> for Ieſus Chriſt hath made the Purgatyon for all youre ſinnes, promiſing that all thoſe that ſhall beleeue in him, and in the Father,<note place="margin">Ihon, 5,</note> who hath ſent him life euerlaſting, and ſhall not come to iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but ſhall paſſe from a ſhort deth to a long life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Take then a good courage in Ieſus Chriſt, for he hath loued you, and waſhed you from all your ſinnes in his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious bloud,<note place="margin">Eſay, 53, Apo, i,</note> take holde in thys ſure faith, to fight tryumphant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye againſt the aduerſary, haue no other ſhielde to defende you withall the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the precious bloud of Ieſus Chryſte, who by the power and might of his death and paſſion,<note place="margin">Rom, v,</note> hath reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled you vnto GOD his Father, vnto whom fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bottome of your hart, in great humilitie and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſay this prayer with me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty and euerlaſtinge Lord God,<note place="margin">Rom, iii, Ihon. xiiii, Math, xxvi, Pſal, xxx,</note> be merciful vnto me poore miſerable ſinner, for thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſte his ſake: and by the merit and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thines of his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, voucheſafe to receiue my ſoule, whiche I commmend into thy handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Take ſure hold tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row hope in this faith,<note place="margin">Iohn, x</note> that our good god ful of all mercy, will &amp; ſhall receiue youre ſoule, as his own, into his hands for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake: for there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name vnder heauen giuen vnto men,<note place="margin">Actes, 4.</note> throughe the whiche we can or may be ſaued, or loke for ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but in Ieſus chriſt arme then your ſelf well with this our good Lord &amp; maſter Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> for he hath done all things for you,<note place="margin">Rom, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> he hath acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law for you, he hath ouer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d al things for you, go to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Reioyce in God,<note place="margin">Hebre. xi</note> be euermore ſtedfaſt in this liuely faith, follow the trace of the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Patriarches, Prophets, and Apoſtles which are all ſaued in this faith, the whiche do all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you that the enemy youre aduerſary cannot annoy you at all, for your ſute is wonne tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough Ieſus Chriſte whiche is your iudge and aduocate alſo.<note place="margin">Ihon, 5, Ihon, 2, Pſal, 23,</note> Wherfore ſay euermore in this firme beleefe, yea althoughe I walke through the valey of the ſhadow of death, yet wil I fere none euil, for thou art with me thy rod and thy ſtaffe comforte me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Do neuer wery youre ſelfe to ſaye from the botome of your hart in this wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty God and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father,<note place="margin">Rom, iii Iohn. xiiii, Math, 2.</note> be merciful vnto me pore miſerable ſiner, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake my lord &amp; ſauiour,
<pb facs="tcp:12885:12"/> and by the merite and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his death and paſſion, voucheſafe to receiue my ſoule the whiche I do moſte humbly commend into thy holy hands, Amen.</p>
               <p>A ſinguler Prayer for a bodye greatly afflicted with ſicknes whiche ſemeth to drawe or ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proche more neere to Death, then to life: with a litle Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thechiſme expreſſely made to inſtruct the ſicke perſon, and to make him behold the great miſtery of our redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Eccleſiaſticus .xviii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Et thee righteouſneſſe before thou come to Iudgement, learne be fore thou ſpeake, &amp; vſe Phiſicke or euer thou be ſicke,<note place="margin">i. Cor. v</note> examine thy ſelf before thou be
<pb facs="tcp:12885:12"/> iudged, and in the day of viſita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion thou ſhalt finde mercye.</p>
               <p>The Lord dooth admoniſhe vs euermore to praye: (ſpeciallye,<note place="margin">Mathe, 2<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</note> when we are touched with hys rods) wherefore all Parentes, and faithfull freendes, whiche ſhall, or do viſite the ſick perſon ought not onely to viſite and ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licitate the bodye, but alſo to ſeeke and demaund the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all medecine for the ſoule which ought to be done by good pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, confeſſion of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mathe, 9.</note> and Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exhortation, according vnto the word of God, without the which no man can liue:<note place="margin">Math, 4,</note> and to thend that all things may be doone in good order, and with good zeale, it ſhalbe conuenient and neceſſary to proſtrate oure ſelues before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſtie of God and ſay vnto him: our help and ſuccoure be in the name of God the Father, the Sonne, and of
<pb facs="tcp:12885:13"/> the holy ghoſte ſo be it, and then ſay this prayer folowinge, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſing generally all your ſins, from the botome of youre hart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Math, xviii</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almighty god and moſte merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we beinge aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of thy welbeloued Son our Lord &amp; ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, we haue vnder the ſelfe ſame Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn. xiiii,</note> preſumed to preſent oure ſelues before thee: to call on thy holy name, haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g oure onely refuge in thy ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine bownty, the which we do not onely deſire to feele &amp; taſte in oure ſelues,<note place="margin">Iames, v</note> but alſo in this the neceſſitie of thy poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, being now afflicted with bodely ſicknes, and troubled in ſpirite,<note place="margin">1. Cor. xi</note> we know O Lorde that iuſtlye thou dooſt puniſhe it in
<pb facs="tcp:12885:13"/> chaſteſing it with thy rods, for to make him vnderſtand thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection,<note place="margin">Pſal, 78,</note> but thy greate mercies, whiche thou vſedſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward oure Fathers are not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed nor conſumed away, for thou art the great and eternall God full of all mercye,<note place="margin">Math, 26,</note> who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dooſt chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge: thy holy word inſtructeth vs full amply, that al the earth is repleniſhed with thy mercies, whiche do ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t far thy iuſtice, wherefore we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche thee O moſt mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ceaſe thy wrath and indig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation towards this thy pore &amp; wretched creature, haue mercye &amp; compaſſion of him for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake: looke not vnto his ſinnes and offences, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the face of thy deare ſon Ieſus Chriſte, who hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye ſatyſfied thee for the ſame, in offeringe vnto thee the greate Sacrifice of hys bodye
<pb facs="tcp:12885:14"/> on the croſſe, for vs miſerable ſinners: we therefore beſeeche the (O God) that art full of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye to let him feele thy mercy &amp; grace, whiche thou neuer didſt refuſe vnto thy beloued ones, and becauſe that thou arte oure heauenly father,<note place="margin">Math, vi,</note> which knowſt all things neceſſary for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: we beſeeche thee not to prolong his life, neither to ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it, for we repoſe oure ſelues on thy holy will, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche deſire onely to accompliſhe and fulfill,<note place="margin">Rom, xi.</note> thou arte wiſe without counſaile to diſpoſe with this thy creature, accordinge to thy good will and pleaſure, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that if it be thy wil O lord to call him, what is he that mai reſiſt it (againe) if thou wilt reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtore him to health,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> who is hee that dare reprooue thee, for all things are in thy hands,<note place="margin">Ihon, i,</note> and no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing is done without thy good
<pb facs="tcp:12885:14"/> will and prouidence: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles O Lorde if by thy grace thou dooſt prolonge his dayes,<note place="margin">Pſal, 2<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> this thy rod ſhalbe vnto him, a chaſtiſinge to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his former life: and ſo bee conuerted vnto thee: and we all with him will yeeld thee thankes for euer: but if thy will bee ſtayed, to make him paſſe vnto a better life: we pray thee in the fauoure of thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſte to forget &amp; do away all his faults &amp; ſinnes the whiche thou haſte vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed to be waſhed in the ſheding of his precious bloud:<note place="margin">Apoca, 1, Math, 26,</note> vouchſafe O Lord by the merite and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the death and paſſion of thy dere ſonne, to receiue his ſoule in to thy holy hands,<note place="margin">Pſal, 30, Pſal, 137,</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall pleaſe thee to call it out of this world: deſpiſe not O lord the worke of thy handes: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thy poore creature almoſt ouerwhelmed, yet callinge on
<pb facs="tcp:12885:15"/> thy name, euen in the midſt of all his troubles and ſorowes, offring thee a wofull and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoule with an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble hart the whiche we pray thee to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, for the loue of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake our Lorde in whoſe name thou haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to exalt our prayers, &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble requeſtes: wherfore we pray thee, receiue vs in to thy holye tuicion, illuminating our harts and vnderſtanding to appeare before thee, and to call on thy holy name as thy beloued So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſte oure Lorde hath taught vs to pray,<note place="margin">Math, vi,</note> for al things neceſſary, ſaying.</p>
               <p>OVre Father whiche arte in Heauen, Hallowed by thy name. Thy kingdome come. Thy wilbe done in earth, as it is in heauen. Giue vs this day our daily bread. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:15"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inally O eternal god and moſt mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, we hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly beſeech thee vouchſafe, to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then vs, by thy grace, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo that by and throughe the weaknes of our fleſhe, wee fall not, and becauſe that of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wee are ſo weake that wee can not, nor may not remaine ſtedfaſt, nor conſtant, no not a minut of an hour: vouchſafe we beſeeche thee to ſtrengthen vs with thy graces, and heauenly benediction, in ſuche ſorte that we remaine conſtant vnto the end in the perfecte faith, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the whiche it is vnpoſſible to pleaſe thee,<note place="margin">Heb, xi</note> confirme this faith in vs euermore, of the whiche we ſhall make confeſſion with hart and mouth ſaying.</p>
               <p>I Beleue in God the Father al mighty maker of Heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:16"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He prayers ended, then may be perceiued howe the ſicke and patient dooth: with inquiſition of his helth, with godly wordes and chriſten talke, and if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſicke perſon decline from this life, &amp; that no likelyhod be ſene in him then may a commodiouſe houre be appointed to ſpeake vnto the ſaid ſick perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to know if he be willing to heare ſpeak of gods woorde to his comfort,<note place="margin">Iohn. viii,</note> whileſt that he is yet in this world and of perfect memorye, and if he be of God, this litle and breef Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thechiſme may be recited as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <p>A breefe Cathechiſme, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſtruct the ſick, but alſo to refreſh his memory, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great miſtery of our redem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ption: the which wel to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande and remember in
<pb facs="tcp:12885:16"/> his latter dayes,<note place="margin">Eccle, 18,</note> he oughte to make confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his faith before the aſſiſtaunce of the faithfull: wherof one of thoſe in the abſence of the Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oughte to queſtion wyth him as foloweth.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nye man that knoweth well him ſelfe,<note place="margin">B.S.N.</note> and doth not omit his condition &amp; qualitie, truly he alſo ought to acknowledge,<note place="margin">Gene, 1, Pſal, li, Ephe, 2,</note> notwithſtandinge that he was created the Image and likenes of God, that he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued and borne in the ſinne of the olde A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam, thorowe the whiche he is become a poore and miſerable ſinner, ignoraunt, inconſtaunt and full of iniquitie, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb facs="tcp:12885:17"/> ſubiect to all miſeries, afflictions, aduerſities, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally vnto death it ſelf,<note place="margin">Rom. 5</note> and all this hath ſinne cauſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which god not leauing it vnpuniſhed. he daily afflicteth vs by ſundry manner wayes, in this worlde to thend that we ſhould not bee dampned with the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>B.S.N.</hi> Haue therfore pati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence in your ſicknes, and ſurely in ſo doing you ſhall poſſes your ſoule in ioyes euerlaſtinge. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your ſinne,<note place="margin">Pſal, 31</note> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe your ſelf before the maieſti of God, the which you muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and contemplat throughe faith, making confeſſion of the ſame, with hart and mouth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the aſſiſtaunce, for it is written: with the hart man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth vnto righteouſneſſe, and with the mouth man confeſſeth to ſaluation, harken then vnto theſe demaunds that ſhal now
<pb facs="tcp:12885:17"/> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye be aſked, and aunſwer faithfully according to the intel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligence that you haue receiued of the Lorde, and if you cannot by reaſon of the weakeneſſe of your ſickneſſe, I will aunſwere for you my ſelfe, and it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vs to haue vnderſtandinge of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant faith, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we all muſt die.</p>
                  <p>Q. I demaund. Wherefore, and to what ende haue you beene created in this world.<note place="margin">Math, 10</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>For to knowe God.<note place="margin">Ge, 2</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Was it not neceſſarye vnto you to knowe God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truly,<note place="margin">Pſal, 17.</note> for ſeinge that hee is my ſoueraygne LORDE,
<pb facs="tcp:12885:18"/> without the knowledge of him I had bene more miſerable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the brute beaſtes.<note place="margin">Pſal, 61, 17</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Seing you knowe GOD, you knowe, that he is my wiſdome, and all infinite goodneſſe, one onely God in perſons three, the Father, the Sonne, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Ghoſte, he is the onely God, that Abraham, Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob haue worſhipped,<note place="margin">Ge, 1, Ihon. i, Luke, i, Gene. 18</note> in ſpirite and truthe, he is the onely and eternall God, which hath made the heauen and alſo the earth, and al things which is in them contayned: the knowledge that you haue of GOD, is it not in this ſorte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>But may ſuche a ſimple know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of God, lead you vnto the life euerlaſting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12885:18"/>
                  <speaker>Sick.</speaker>
                  <p>Very hardelye: for it is life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge to confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge one onely God,<note place="margin">Ihon. xvii.</note> and he whom he hath ſent, his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſonne our Lorde and ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore is it neceſſary to acknowledge, and confeſſe the Lorde and Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe, that I muſt recouer in Ieſu Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 5 Pſal, li, Luke. xxiiii Pſal. 2, Rom, xi</note> all that I haue loſt in my ſelfe, by reaſon of the ſinne committed by Adam oure fore father, in the whiche I am conceiued and born: ſo that now it was neceſſary for my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Ieſus Chriſte the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God, both God and man, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with our fleſh, ſhould geue me through his grace and free mercy, all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had loſt in Adam</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12885:19"/>
                  <p>It is very well ſayde, that is the cauſe,<note place="margin">Math, 1,</note> why Ieſus Chriſte was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued by the holy ghoſt and borne of the virgin Mary, for to purge and ſanctifye you, for all together contrarye vnto him,<note place="margin">Ephe, 2, Rom, viii,</note> are you borne and concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſinne, and ſinful Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wherfore you muſt confes that without Ieſus Chriſt, you had remained a pore and miſerable ſinner in euerlaſting Death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 5</note>I truly, but I beleue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conciled mee vnto God his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>How hathe he reconciled you to God his father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math, 26,</note>By his death and paſſion, &amp; by the ſhedding of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, for I knowe &amp; am
<pb facs="tcp:12885:19"/> fullye perſwaded, that Ieſus Chriſt hath ſuffred vnder Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Pilate, diuers and many afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note place="margin">Acts, 3.</note> iniuries, and tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to deliuer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternall death it is Ieſus Chriſte whiche hath beene crucyfied for mee,<note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed vpon the tree of the cros, to deliuer me from the maledic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of rhe Deuil, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Adam had bound me vnto, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte hath bene truly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, for to burye all my ſinnes, becauſe they may not be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto me before God: it is mi Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt whiche is deſcended into Hell, ſuffring an extreame agony, for to deliuer me from the eternall Pitte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Is all that you haue confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Ieſus Chriſte preſentlye ſufficient for to ſaue you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sick.</speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12885:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 53, Math, xxvi,</note>No, but that it was requiſite that the holy ſcriptures, mighte in all thinges be accompliſhed, for what had it profited me, for Ieſus Chriſt to haue ben born crucified, dead, buried, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into hell for me onely: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out the reſurrection: wherefore I beleue and confeſſe that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is riſen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead for to make me riſe with him as one of his little members, into euerlaſting life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>It is conſequently writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he is aſſended in Heauen, and their preſently ſet on the right hande of God his Father, but what auayleth this aſſencion vnto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>My cheef and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte is aſſended into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for to make me aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d after him, for where the head is, there the
<pb facs="tcp:12885:20"/> members be alſo, and I beleue that he beinge ſet on the right hande of God his Father,<note place="margin">2. Iohn, 2</note> is my aduocate, interceſſors, ond one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mediatour towardes him,<note place="margin">Rom, viii,</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring me that none can hinder me ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſꝰ Chriſt is my me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diatour,<note place="margin">Ihon, 5,</note> and my iudge all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: wherefore I neede not to feare the day of his coming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement: when hee ſhall come to iudge the quick and the dead,<note place="margin">Math, 2<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</note> for I beleue and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with ſtedfaſt faithe, that there is neither iudgement nor condemnation, towardes or for thoſe which be his faythful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſtre.</speaker>
                  <p>Who hath geuen you grace to knowe and vnderſtand al theſe thinges.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sick.</speaker>
                  <p>It is throughe the grace of the holy ghoſte, one onely God,
<pb facs="tcp:12885:21"/> with the Father, and the ſonne by whoſe meanes we receiue al good gifts, which are offred vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Seing that you haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy confeſſed that you be the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ieſus Chriſt, it alſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that you bee incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto his Churche, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche you muſt beleue to be holye, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and vniuerſall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sick.</speaker>
                  <p>I beleue ſtedfaſtly the holy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall churche, waſhed and purified in the precious blud of Ieſus Chriſte, for the whiche moſt humbly I thank him, that he hath vouchſafed me to be as one of the litle members of his churche, and being baptiſed in his name, hath vouchſafed me to liue in the communion,<note place="margin">Math, 4.</note> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and charitie of the ſame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his holy worde
<pb facs="tcp:12885:21"/> and fed with his perfect body, &amp; quenched with his precioꝰ blud in hope of euerlaſting life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Now ſeinge you be grounded on the liuely roke,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x</note> whiche is Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte in knowinge youre ſelfe, you muſte acknowledge &amp; confeſſe the principall benefit, that you haue receiued of oure Lord and Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sicke.</speaker>
                  <p>It is reaſon and very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, for I wil not be vnthankful to acknowledge the gifts and benefites that I haue receaued of God:<note place="margin">Pſal, li,</note> wherefore I confeſſe &amp; acknowledg that I pore and mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner, haue offended di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers and ſundry wayes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, in tranſgreſſinge his commaundementes in the whiche ſo doing, I haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued deth &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding flying vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:12885:22"/> mercy of God. I craue and aſke mercy beleuing and confeſſing vndoubtedly, that ful remiſſion of ſinnes is graunted me, by the onely death and paſſion of my Lorde and ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte, and in the ſheading of his precious bloode,<note place="margin">Hebre. i,</note> in whome and throughe whome I aſſure my ſelfe to be wholye waſhed &amp; purged, whiche is the greateſt gifte and contentation,<note place="margin">Math, x,</note> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer coulde haue hapened vnto me, and ſuche is my faith in the which I will liue and dye, mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of the holy ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Seing you haue receyued ſo great gifts of God, by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte it is alſo conuenient and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary, that you follow the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemenet, for euen as hee hathe forgeuen you, and made ſatiſfaction for all your ſinnes,
<pb facs="tcp:12885:22"/> ſo likewiſe you muſte forgeeue from the botome of youre hart vnto all thoſe that haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you, els you walke not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to gods lawes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sick.</speaker>
                  <p>In this I haue knowen the lawe of Ieſus Chriſte to be the only holy and perfect doctrine commaunding vs to loue oure neighbours, frendes,<note place="margin">Math. xix,</note> and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as our ſelues: wherfore I pray vnto al thoſe that I haue offended by thought, worde, or deede, to forgeue me with as free a will and good hart, as I forgeue all thoſe that haue offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded or treſpaſſed againſt me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſirous to doe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good as vnto my louers and frendes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>Seing that God hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that all men ſhall dye,<note place="margin">Gene. 3</note> wee cannot reſiſt his ordinaunce, &amp; therefore we ought to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:12885:23"/> vnto his will, wherefore dere brother you may not think it ſtraunge, though I annouce vnto you the wordes of Eſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet te that hee declared and ſpake vnto king Eſechias,<note place="margin">Eſay, 38.</note> ſaying in the behalfe of God.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſaith the Lorde, ſet thy houſe in an order, for thou muſt dye, and ſhalt not liue: this good counſell ought to occaſion you, to diſpoſe your ſelfe ſpiritually in youre conſcience, and firſt to perſwade your ſelf to godwarde and wepe and lament your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Eſay, 55,</note> as this good Kinge did, craue his mercy, in aſking him forgeuenes, and euermore ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your harte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Lorde God thou mercifull and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull vnto me pore and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinner, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake my Lorde and ſauioure, and then you may not forgette your houſe &amp; familye, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:12885:23"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
